现在我们已经看了格式化字符串
so now that we've taken a look at format strings
以及它应该如何在函数如printf中使用
and how format strings are supposed to be used with functions such as printf
我们来探索如何用它来泄露数据
let's start exploring how we can abuse format strings to leak data
当然，这不是它最初的用途
that may not have originally been intended
请记住，使用格式化字符串时
now keep in mind when we're using format strings
我们能控制如何展示泄露数据
we have control over how the data being leaked is represented
我们能用%c来作为单个字符展示
so we could use percent C to display data as a single character
这样能泄露1字节
that would give us a single byte
如果这就是我们要的，那很好
if that's all we need then that's great
但是如果我们想泄漏的不止1字节
but if we wanted to leak more than a single byte
我们可以用%d或%i
we could use percent d or percent i
这会以十进制整数形式泄露4字节
and that would leak four bytes displayed as a decimal integer
如果十六进制更容易处理的话
if hexadecimal was easier to work with
我们就可以用%x
we could use percent x
可以泄露同样的4字节
and we could leak those same 4 bytes
但是会用十六进制来展示
but get it displayed in hexadecimal format
%s，用于显示字符串
now percent s which is intended to be used to display a string
特别强大
is particularly powerful
因为它的作用是
because what it does is
解引用指针，并读出任意个字节
it dereferences a pointer and reads out an arbitrary number of bytes
这些字节可能是可显，或不可显的
now these bytes may be printable or not printable
都会被读出
but they will still be read out
直到遇到null字节
and they will continue to be read out until a null byte is encountered
格式化字符串也能用大小前缀，或叫大小修饰符
format strings also utilize size prefixes or size modifiers
这里能看到，%x一般泄露4字节
here we see that percent x normally leaks out 4 bytes
如果加上h前缀
however if you prefix it with h
你会得到2字节的16进制数
you would get a hexadecimal representation of only 2 bytes
hhx 则会泄露1字节的16进制数
hhx would leak 1 byte as a hexadecimal value
如果想泄露更多
now if we wanted to leak a larger amount
可以用%l，这是long的缩写
we can use percent l which is shorthand for long
这样可以泄露8字节，也可用%lx
so we could leak 8 bytes or long hex
我们来看一看
let's take a look
为了探索这个问题
so in order to explore this
我们写一个有漏洞的c程序
let's write a vulnerable C program
我们include
we're going to include stdio.h
因为我们想调用printf
cause we want to call printf
我们给printf传入个格式化字符串
we're going to call printf on some format string
然后返回
and then just return 0
这个格式化字符串
now the format string
就放在栈上
is just gonna be here on the stack
把argv[1]拷贝到该格式化字符串
we will copy whatever is in argv[1] to that format string
然后追加个换行符
and then we'll append a new line on there
这样就不会看到垃圾数据了
so that we don't have the garbage
给printf传入0xBEEF1337 （leet）
and let's pass this value of BEEF1337
然后
and then
我们在栈上放一个任意字符串
let's put an arbitrary string on the stack here
我们声明一个 secret_value
so we'll have secret value
然后让编译器满意
and then make the compiler happy
我们把需要的头文件都引入
we will include a couple more header files
如果我们编译好这个
and if we compile this
再给它
and we'll give it
%d，会得到一个很小的负数
percent d. we get a giant negative number
传入%c，会得到7
if we do percent C we just get 7
这没问题
well this does make sense
最后一个字节不是7
like 7 isn't the end of this
最后一个字节是37
and the last byte here is 37
%c将最低有效字节，这里的37，作为一个字符解读
percent C interprets the least significant byte which in this case is 37 as a character
0x37就是字符7
and hex 37 is the character 7
所以我们才会看到这个
which is why we see this here
%d 显示一个很小的负数
now percent d shows us a giant negative number
这看不出什么
which isn't particularly useful
如果改用 ld
if we did a long decimal
一下值就变正的了
well now all of a sudden the value is positive
这是因为最高有效位是0
and that's because the most significant bit is not set
所以它突然变成了正数
so it is suddenly a positive number
通常会用的是%x
often times what you want to see is percent x
我们已经习惯了十六进制格式
we're used to seeing things in hexadecimal format
如果输出 leak: 0x%x
so if you were to do something like leak 0x percent x
结果会很像我们在GDB或IDA中看到的
this is now very similar to the type of things that we'd see in GDB or in IDA
特别是说到内存地址
when we're talking about memory addresses
或者内存地址的值
or we're talking about looking at values at the memory
除了x，还可以用 lx
now instead of just x we could do lx
这个例子中，因为值不够大，没更高字节了
now in this case because there are no higher bytes in this number
所以结果不会变
the value doesn't change
不止这些，现在只是正常查看这个值
but not only that because right now we're just looking at the intended value
这里只放了一个格式记号
we just have one format specifier here
有一个我喜欢用的，ppt没写的，%p
now one that I like to use that isn't in the slides is percent P
这是指针的简写
which is shorthand for pointer
如果我们用%p
and so if we do percent P
得到的还是0xbeef1337
we still get 0xbeef1337
但它比lx少输入一个字符
but it's one less character than lx
我们可以指定多个记号
we can specify multiple of these
这就开始有趣了
and now it's kind of interesting
因为现在能看到原来printf中没有的值了
cause now we're starting to see values that are not in the original printf call
因为我们能控制这个格式化字符串
because we control this format string
如果我们一直写%p
if we just keep putting percent p
printf会持续输出指针
printf will just keep producing pointers
我不用知道它们指向的是什么
now I don't necessarily know what these are pointers to
有beef1337，有1a
cause we have beef1337 we have 1a
这泄露出 RDX的值是1a
now this 1a is a leak of what is in RDX
所以我们获得了关于程序内部状态的信息
so we are gaining information about what is kind of the internal state of the program
但如果我想拿到我的secret_value呢
but what if I want to get my secret value
secret_value是一个局部变量
well my secret value is a local variable
它在main里面，也就是说它在栈上
it's inside main which means it is on the stack
如果我一直%p
so if I just keep doing percent p
我应该能遇到一个像栈地址的值
I should come across something that looks like a stack address
确实遇到了
and I do
这个5560 看起来像一个栈指针
this 5560 this right here looks like a stack pointer
这是倒数第三个
and that is third from the end here
不对，倒数第二个
no second from the end
它应该是这个值
so it should be this value right here
如果我把p换成s
if I change that p to an s
就会解引用这个指针
we're now going to dereference that address
并打印出null前的所有字节
and print out all of the bytes until a terminating null byte is encountered
一下，就从这个程序中泄露出了secret_value
and so suddenly we've leaked out my secret value from this binary
尽管只给printf传了0xbeef1337
despite the fact that printf is only supplied with 0xbeef1337
在这个例子中
so in that example
我们只是一直用%p，直到找到有趣的东西
we just spammed percent p until we found something interesting
再从那里开始探索
and then kind of explored it from there
要是我们准确知道感兴趣的是哪个参数呢
but what if we know exactly what parameter we're interested in
我想把第32个参数按16进制字符打印出来
I want to print the 32nd parameter as a hex string
我能做到吗，或者是否需要32个%p
can I do that or do I need to have 32 percent P's to get there
你可以做的更简单
well you can do something a little bit more concise
你可以在格式化字符串中用 $
and that is you can take advantage of the dollar sign operator inside your format string
$ 能让我们指定感兴趣的参数
the dollar sign operator allows us to specify what parameter we're interested in
在这张幻灯片中的 %7$x
so in the slide here we have percent 7$x
这指的是，按16进制打印第7个参数
which specifies that we want to print the 7th parameter as a hexadecimal value
我们知道第7个参数在栈上
now we know that the 7th parameter is on the stack
所以就可以泄露想要的栈上的值了
so we can start leaking stack values that we target
看看能不能用在这个例子上
so let's see if we can use that on the example that we have here
我对这个字符串值很感兴趣
so I was interested in this string value
我们数一下，这是第几个参数
so let's count and see how many arguments along was it
1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8
看起来是9
looks like nine
我可以执行 a.out
so I can do a.out
还是输出 leak:
we'll still have a leak
%9$s
percent 9 $ s
现在不会输出这些垃圾数据了
and now I don't have all of that garbage
我能指定我感兴趣的参数
I was able to target the specific parameter that I was interested in
我们能在下个视频中看到这是多么强大
and this is surprisingly powerful coz we'll see in the next video here
我刚刚讲的例子
now the example that I just ran through
漏洞很严重，因为用户能完全控制格式化字符串
is somewhat trivial in the sense that the user has full control of the format string
并能设置成他们想要的任意值
and can set it to whatever they desire
这种情况市面上确实有
however that does happen sometimes in the wild
还有些没这么严重的格式化字符串漏洞
there are less trivial format string vulnerabilities
比如动态生成的格式化字符串
some examples would be like a dynamically generated format string
用户不能直接提供格式化字符串
where the user may not provide the format string literally
而是基于他们的行为
but based on actions they take
构造一个特定的恶意格式化字符串
they can help construct a specific format string that is malformed
可能导致printf错误解析数据
this may cause printf to be called that will interpret data incorrectly
比如，用%s解析一个指针
for example calling percent s on a pointer that is in a string
这会泄露大量的数据
that's going to leak a large amount of data
还有其它printf之外的函数
now there are also other functions that are not printf
例如sprintf，它用格式化字符串来构建字符串
such as sprintf which uses a format string to build a string
或snprintf，它限制了长度，但做的事一样
or snprintf which limits the length but does the same thing
还有被用于输入的格式化字符串
we also see format strings being used to take an input
例如sscanf或scanf
such as sscanf or scanf
最后，还有用于日志的
and lastly we have format strings being used for logging
比如常见的fprintf
this is somewhat common where you see fprintf
这个会根据格式化字符串构建字符串
which is going to construct a string from a format string
然后写到文件中
and then write it out to a file
这些依赖格式化字符串的函数都是潜在的可利用对象
any one of these functions that rely on format strings are potentially exploitable
接下来我们应牢记这一点
and so we should keep that in mind going forward